[Music]
Hi everyone. We're back for another
episode of the USADA pitch and I'm
joined today by two special guests.
First, I want to welcome Chris Quitant
who is the director of high performance
athlete services for USA track and
field. Chris, thank you so much for
being here.
>> Yeah, thanks everybody. Glad to be here.
And we work really closely with Chris to
make sure that track and field athletes
are both well educated and well tested
so that we can be confident that a clean
team USA is lining up at competitions
around the world. One of the people
Chris works with the most at USADA is
our director of elite education, Tammy
Hansen. Welcome back to another episode,
Tammy.
>> Thanks, Avery. Always a pleasure.
So today we want to dive into how and
why USADA and NGBS like USA track and
field work together ahead of major
events including outdoor championships
which are right around the corner
happening July 31st through August 3rd
in Eugene, Oregon. So Chris and Tammy,
when it comes to outdoor championships
and other big events, where do you all
start? When does planning begin?
>> Yeah, I think planning uh literally
starts at the end of every championship.
Uh so for 2025, I think we started right
at the end of our championship in 2024.
Uh kind of reviewing the process, pros
and cons, what worked, what didn't work,
um how we can further collaborate, how
we can improve on some of the processes
that we have in our collaboration at our
championships. Um and then specifically
with Tammy and her education team, we do
have a year-end uh review that we do
every year. So we not only look at our
championships, but all the engagements
we have throughout the year. Um and
again like I said kind of um try and
review have a better understanding of
how we can collaborate further and what
US track and field can do to to further
the efforts um you know that USADA has
on their on their plate. So yeah.
>> Yeah. Absolutely. And one of the other
things that US track and field and USADA
both really lean into is collaboration
with the athletes integrity unit. So uh
we work with them collaborate uh figure
out if they're going to be able to
attend and provide some education at the
events as well. and whether they are or
aren't. Uh we work really closely on
messaging, making sure that where we can
align and educate the athletes on some
of the common things that we're seeing
or common questions that the athletes
have. Uh together, the three
organizations really do want to work
closely together to make sure that we're
all moving forward and educating
athletes and their support people as
well as we can.
>> Nice. So, that's a good segue. Tammy,
can you tell me more about your strategy
for educating these groups and how Chris
and his team support that process?
>> Yeah, you know, the um USA TF team has
just been incredible to work with. So,
it's really important to start with
understanding our audience. Uh so, Chris
and the team are always in the field,
always talking to the athletes. So, they
really have a good understanding of who
might be new to testing, uh, who's kind
of been around for a really long time,
what common questions or trends they're
seeing, so they can set us up to be
ready to answer those questions, to be
able to dump jump right in on messaging,
uh, and to know what level of details.
So, if we're seeing an athlete and it's
their first time, we know that they
might have a lot more questions. Whereas
if it's someone who's been with us for a
long time, uh maybe not so specific um
or less detail.
>> Yeah, absolutely. So, what about when
you get to the event? What does
education look like there?
>> And again, um such a great partner. So,
they first of all ensure that we're
ready and ready to be successful at the
event. So they ensure that we have a
good booth location, get us the
credentials that we need to have access,
and then they introduce us to anyone
that we might need to know or have
contact with throughout the event. Uh
obviously as events always have schedule
changes or life happens at the event, uh
they ensure that we're educated and up
to date on what we might need to know.
And then they're also again going kind
of back to that messaging piece. If we
know that the event is happening in a
country where maybe contamination is
prevalent or uh there's maybe stricter
rules about what medications can be
brought in, uh we kind of design a
little bit of an elevator pitch for the
athletes where we're maximizing their
time, getting them in and out of a team
processing type setting, uh where they
come to our table, we give them the the
quick information that they need, we're
there to answer any questions that they
might have, and then we send them on
their way. So we really strategize on
what are the most important messaging
components that the athletes need right
before going on to maybe a world
championship or a even bigger
competition. What are those last minute
things that they would need to know?
>> Yeah, for sure. And Chris, can you tell
us a little bit more about your team's
process during um event education?
>> Yeah, I think Tammy kind of hit the nail
on the head there. I mean, we want to
make sure we collaborate with all our
partners, right? So, we collaborate with
a lot of um organizations, individuals
to pull off our championships. Uh
obviously, we have LLC's, we have
volunteers, um and USADA plays a large
role in what we do at our championships,
right? So, we want to make sure they're
set up. Tammy mentioned having full
access, uh credentiing, making sure they
have full scope of what our championship
looks like, the setup, not only on the
field of play, but also, um you know,
the education opportunity, and Tammy
mentioned our team processing. So, if
you're not familiar, um whenever we have
a championship and athletes qualify for
a particular team, we have a full
immersive process where the athlete does
everything that they may need for that
championship. So, that goes from making
sure they have their background safe
sport um credentials kind of up to date.
Uh booking travel, connecting and
registering with coaches um and then
USADA education team plays a large role
in that too. So, they're one of the
required boxes that need to get checked.
So, uh it's kind of a mandate that we
have all our athletes go through that
process. Um, and as they mentioned, not
every athlete, depending on their level,
how long they've been in the RTP, they
might have different levels of of of
questions or engagement. Uh, but we want
to make sure that there's still that
touch point with the education team, uh,
before they, you know, travel onto this
team. Um, and that's the biggest impact
I think we kind of set up for the
education team is that face to face
interaction. Tim and I talk about all
the time of what are the different ways
we can reach out to athletes, how we can
engage and quite honestly um I think um
team processing and that face to face
engagement is probably the the biggest
impact we have. As Tammy mentioned,
they're going to kind of potentially a
foreign land that the rules might be a
little different. So, um making sure the
team is prepared with that information
to provide to our athletes um plays a
huge role and I think it's a big impact
for our athletes.
>> Yeah. And I would just add into that,
you know, that's one of the things
that's so cool about our collaboration
with track and field as well is for a
lot of events, uh, USADA, when we have a
booth or we have some sort of event
education, it might be in like an expo
center where people might be passing by
and see us and we'll engage in
conversations when they have questions.
Uh, but with the track and field events,
we are guaranteed to get to see every
single athlete who's going to go to that
world championships. And so it's again
just that opportunity for any last
minute questions. We want to make sure
that every Team USA athlete and every
athlete representing USA track and field
and the US uh goes there and does that
and does really well and and that they
know everything that they need to know
from a clean sport perspective before
they even leave the US. And so our
ability collaboratively to do that, the
investment that USATF has made into uh
making that a requirement and having us
part of team processing has really
helped our ability globally uh to make
sure that every athlete that ever
attends one of those events has been
educated.
>> True.
>> Yeah. What an amazing thing to be able
to do. So what about testing, Chris? Who
do you collaborate with? What does that
collaboration look like for the event?
Yeah, it's uh fully immersive. Uh just
like what we do for the education team,
we do for the testing team as well,
right? So um you know the client
services team and uh the lead DCOS that
are assigned to our championships. Uh we
collaborate them. Uh like I mentioned,
as soon as one championship ends, we
start talking about what next year looks
like. So over the past couple months,
we've been um connecting with our LLC's,
connecting with the lead DCOS, um
talking about what the championship's
going to look like, obviously the the
requirements, access credentials, what
the setup is going to be like, how many
dope control stations are are they going
to need, what are the volunteer needs
for chaperons, right? Uh that's a huge
requirement for the dope control
station. So collaborate with the LLC,
making sure that the lead DCO is
comfortable with the number of
volunteers um and make sure we game plan
for, you know, 10 eventually before life
happens, right? So we may not always
meet all the requirements that you know
have a to have a perfect do control
station but uh figure it out on the fly
and collaborate uh with those DCOs. So
uh my role and and my uh co-workers role
during a championship we're we're kind
of the middleman if you will, right? So
the LLC does a lot of the work on the
front end to run our championship and
then we have our DCOS that are you know
post competition that are selecting
athletes and going through the total
control process. Um and I try to make
life um as easy as possible for those
DCOs. So, they're running out of
supplies, water, Gatorade. Um, if
they're looking for an athlete, if um,
you know, Ted mentioned the schedule
changes, we want to make sure we're
communicating that. Um, if they're
confused on who an athlete is, right? We
have a lot of athletes. We sometimes
have 150 to 160 athletes that might
qualify for a team. So, a lot of faces
that they kind of need to know on the
fly, especially after competition. So,
making sure that they have an
understanding of who those athletes are.
So, anything we can do from USATF to
make sure that DCOS's are comfortable,
um, are prepared, and that they're
focused on what they need to do. Um,
that's really where we collaborate, make
sure that, um, you know, we're doing
everything we can. So,
>> yeah, what an awesome group effort. So,
speaking of the group, uh, Tammy
mentioned the athletics integrity unit
uh, a little bit earlier, but can you
tell us more about the collaboration
that helps happens with that group and,
um, what more does that look like?
>> For sure. So we have very similar
engagements with the AIU just like we do
with USADA. Um obviously being kind of
the the anti-doping agency for for our
international federation. Um and
obviously there's some anti-doping
compliance rule 15 that as a member
federation you know we need to stay in
compliance with. So from a regulation
standpoint um you know required to meet
certain standards throughout the year um
whether it be education testing pool
communicate our long list for certain
championships things like that. We just
have to kind of engage with AIOU. But um
there's also some proactive
collaboration. So um the AIU will also
be at our championship. They they've
been there for the past probably two
seasons now. Um I think they've realized
the impact that you guys have at our
championship. So they also want to
collaborate um on on that front as well.
So there's a high level of proactive um
collaboration with AIOU um just like we
do at USADA and that continues to grow
and I think uh between the three
organizations USADA um USA track and
field AIU we've kind of built a good
system of communication to be able to um
understand what that message should be
out to athletes and make sure we're all
on the same page when we are um
communicating rules, regulations,
anything like that to athletes.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And Tammy, can you
talk a little bit more about when
testing starts and what is the process
around ratifying records because that's
obviously um something that could happen
at these big events?
>> Yeah, absolutely. So, agencies like
USADA are allowed to test athletes
before, during, and after competition.
So to make sure that we're testing at
the right times, we often team up with
national governing bodies to really keep
us up to date on those competition
schedules, start lists, registrations,
you know, training information, and
anything else that would help us know
when and how and who to test. Uh, you
know, Chris mentioned 160 athletes.
We've even run into situations where
sometimes they have the same name. So,
uh, really working through and
collaborating to make sure we're
identifying the right athlete at the
right time is imperative. Uh, also
important to know that in competition
period usually starts at 11:59 the night
before any event. So that's also why
we're paying really close attention to
timing for that particular athletes
event. Um, so that we can apply the
right prohibited list and really just
make sure that everything is fair and
accurate for that athlete that we're
testing. Uh and then when it comes to
ratifying records, so uh some people
might be surprised to find out that
anytime a record is hit, um they do have
to have a test, a anti-doping uh sample
collection test in order to ratify that
record. So as soon as that happens, uh
we are collaborating really closely with
USA track and field to make sure that we
can get that test completed to ensure
for the athletes sake that they are able
to uphold that record.
>> Yeah. had to follow up on that. There's
uh as you can imagine, it can be kind of
tricky. You don't know. You never really
know when a world or national record is
going to happen. So, from our front, we
try to make sure we're tracking
athletes. We kind of have an
understanding where they are throughout
the season. So, if at certain times of
the year, we kind of have an
understanding of when an athlete is
maybe trending to break a record, we
might communicate that to USADA. Um and
if we just if it happens out of nowhere,
uh we sometimes we do get those
communications. Um you know, morning,
noon, and night, you know, we'll get
those calls. So, we'll try to
proactively work with USADA and if it's
myself, my co-orker or sometimes the
athlete um reaches out to USADA through
their hotline um to to you know make
sure they set up dop control. Um
obviously from member federation
standpoint there's um a lot of
additional requirements when we talk
about ratifying record but I think the
first step is um having that test
completed. So, um, again, the
collaboration that we have with USADA
plays a large role in our ability to
communicate when those things happen,
making sure we have understanding of our
sport, um, and, um, some of the
requirements that go with those records.
So, um, I'm grateful of the
collaboration and the partnership with
we have USADA, cuz quite honestly, in
the end, we're all here for the
athletes, and anything we can do to make
that process even easier, it's just, um,
I think it's a win for us. So, uh, we
appreciate the collaboration on on
USADA's end.
>> Well said, Chris. and we appreciate it
as well. All right, everyone. I think
that um is going to do it for today. We
pulled back the curtain a bit on
education and testing for major events.
Uh and you can always find uh more
information on USADA.org. Tammy and
Chris, thank you so much uh to you both
for being here.
>> Yeah, thank you. And thanks, Chris.
>> Thanks. Appreciate it.
>> And watch out for more episodes of the
USA pitch.
[Music]